In this video, we will learn about deep
learning algorithms. We will start with
supervised deep learning algorithms, and
in this video, we will learn about
convolutional neural networks.
Convolutional neural networks are very
similar to the neural networks that we
have seen so far in this course. They are
made up of neurons, which need to have
the weights and biases optimized. Each
neuron combines the inputs that it
receives by computing the dot product
between each input and the corresponding
weight before it fits the resulting
total input into an activation function,
ReLU most likely. So then, what is
different with these networks and why
are they called convolutional neural
networks?
Well convolutional neural networks, or
CNNs for short, make the explicit
assumption that the inputs are images,
which allows us to incorporate certain
properties into their architecture. These
properties make the forward propagation
step much more efficient and vastly
reduces the amount of parameters in the
network. Therefore, CNNs are best for
solving problems related to image
recognition, object detection, and other
computer vision applications. Here is a
typical architecture of a convolutional
neural network. As you can see, the
network consists of a series of
convolutional, ReLU,  and pooling layers
as well as a number of fully connected
layers which are necessary before the
output is generated. Now, let's study what
happens in each layer. So far, we have dealt
only with conventional neural networks
that take an ( n x 1) vector as their
input. The input to a convolutional
neural network, on the other hand, is
mostly an (n x m x 1) for grayscale images
or an (n x m x 3) for colored images,
where the number 3 represents the
red,
green, and blue components of each pixel
in the image. In the convolutional layer,
we basically define filters and we
compute the convolution between the
defined filters and each of the three
images. If we take the red image for
example, let's assume these are the pixel
values. Now for a (2 x 2) filter with
these values, let's create an empty
matrix to save the results of the
convolution process.
We start by sliding the filter over the
image and computing the dot product
between the filter and the overlapping
pixel values and storing the result in
the empty matrix. We repeat this step
moving our filter one cell, or one stride
is the proper terminology, at a time, and
we repeat this until we cover the entire
image and fill the empty matrix. Here, I
just showed one filter and only one of
the three images. The same thing would be
applied to the green and blue images and
you can apply more than one filter. The
more filters we use, the more we are able
to preserve the spatial dimensions
better. But one question you must be
asking yourself at this point is, why
would we need to use convolution? Why not
flatten the input image into an (n x m) x 1
vector and use that as our input?
Well, if we do that, we will end up with a
massive number of parameters that will
need to be optimized, and it will be
super computationally expensive. Also,
decreasing the number of parameters
would definitely help in preventing the
model from overfitting the training data.
It is worth mentioning that a
convolutional layer also consists of
ReLU's which filter the output of the
convolutional step passing only positive
values and turning any negative values
to 0. The next layer in our
convolutional neural network is the
pooling layer. The pooling layer's main
objective is to reduce the spatial
dimensions of the data propagating
through the network. There are two types
of pooling that are widely used in
convolutional neural networks. Max-
pooling and average pooling. In max-pooling
which is the most common of the
two, for each section of the image we scan
we keep the highest value, like so.
Here our filter is moving two strides at
a time.
Similarly, with average pooling, we
compute the average of each area we scan.
In addition to reducing the dimension of
the data, pooling, or max pooling in
particular, provides spatial variance
which enables the neural network to
recognize objects in an image even if
the object does not exactly resemble the
original object. Finally, in the fully
connected layer, we flatten the output
of the last convolutional layer and
connect every node of the current layer
with every other node of the next layer.
This layer basically takes as input the
output from the preceding layer, whether
it is a convolutional layer, ReLU, or
pooling layer, and outputs an n-dimensional
vector, where n is the number
of classes pertaining to the problem at
hand. For example, if you are building a
network to classify images of digits, the
dimension n would be 10, since there are
10 digits. You will be covering
convolutional neural networks in much
more details in the other courses in this
specialization, but this information is
more than enough to give you a general
understanding of convolutional neural
networks. Now let's see how we can use
the Keras library to build a
convolutional neural network. Here I will
show you how you can use the Keras
library to build a convolutional neural
network. Training and testing of a
convolutional neural network are the
same as what we have seen so far. So to
begin with, we use the sequential
constructor to create our model. Then, we
define our input to be the size of the
input images. Assuming the input images
are 128 by 128 color images, we define
the input shape to be a tuple of (128, 128, 3).
Next, we start adding layers to the
network. We start with a convolutional
layer, with 16 filters, each filter being
of size 2x2 and slides through the image
with a stride of magnitude 1 in the
horizontal direction, and of magnitude 1
in the vertical direction. And the layer
uses the ReLU activation function. Then,
we add a pooling layer and we're using
max-pooling here with a filter or
pooling size of 2 and the filter slides
through the image with a stride of
magnitude 2. Next, we add another set of
convolutional and pooling layers. The
only difference here is we are using more
filters in the convolutional layer,
actually twice as many filters as the
first convolutional layer. Finally, we
flatten the output from these layers so
that the data can proceed to the fully
connected layers. We add another dense
layer with 100 nodes and an output layer
that has nodes equal to the number of
classes in the problem at hand. And we
use the softmax activation function in
order to convert the outputs into
probabilities. With this, we conclude this
video on convolutional neural networks.
In the lab, we will implement a complete
convolutional neural network, where we
will use the Keras library to build the
network, train it, and then validate it. So
make sure to complete this module's lab
on convolution learning networks.