So far, we discussed two supervised deep
learning models, which are the
convolutional neural network and the
recurrent neural network. In this video, we
will switch to an unsupervised deep
learning model which is the autoencoder.
So what are autoencoders? Autoencoding
is a data compression algorithm where
the compression and the decompression
functions are learned automatically from
data. instead of being engineered by a
human. Such autoencoders are built using
neural networks. Autoencoders are data
specific, which means that they will only
be able to compress data similar to what
they have been trained on. Therefore, an
autoencoder
trained on pictures of cars would do a
rather poor job of compressing pictures
of buildings, because the features it
would learn would be vehicle or car
specific. Some interesting applications
of autoencoders are data denoising and
dimensionality reduction for data
visualization. Here is the architecture of
an autoencoder. It takes an image, for
example, as an input and uses an encoder
to find the optimal compressed
representation of the input image. Then,
using a decoder the original image is
restored. So an autoencoder is an
unsupervised neural network model. It
uses backpropagation by setting the
target variable to be the same as the
input. In other words, it tries to learn
an approximation of an identity function.
Because of non-linear activation
functions in neural networks,
autoencoders can learn data projections
that are more interesting than a
principal component analysis PCA or
other basic techniques, which can handle
only linear transformations. A very
popular type of autoencoders is the
Restricted Boltzmann Machines or (RBMs) for short. RBMs have been successfully
used for various applications, including
fixing imbalanced datasets. Because
RBMs learn the input in order to be
able to
regenerate it, then they can learn the
distribution of the minority class in an
imbalance dataset ,and then generate more data points of that class, transforming
the imbalance dataset into a balanced
data set.
Similarly, RBMs can also be used to
estimate missing values in different
features of a data set. Another popular
application of Restricted Boltzmann
Machines is automatic feature extraction
of especially unstructured data. And this
concludes our high-level introduction to
autoencoders and Restricted Boltzmann
Machines.