In this video, we will start learning how
to use the Keras library to build deep
learning models. We will start with
building models for regression problems.
In this course, we will be using
Cognitive Class Labs, or CC Labs for
short, as our platform to run the lab
sessions. So if you go to labs.cognitiveclass.ai,
you can either sign in if
you already have a Cognitive Class
account, or sign up if this is your first
visit to Cognitive Class or its Labs
platform. Once you sign in you should get
to this landing page, where you can
select different environments. Let's
click on JupyterLab to start a new
JupyterLab Notebook.
Once JupyterLab loads, click on the
Python 3 icon to start a new notebook. In
order to avoid any technical hiccups, or
to make sure that you have the smoothest
experience, we have pre-installed the
Keras library in CC Labs so you can
import it directly by running "import
keras". Once the code executes, it will
print what backend was used to install
the Keras library. Here, we used the
TensorFlow backend. Let's take a look at
a regression example. Here is a data set
of the compressive strength of different
samples of concrete based on the volumes
of the different materials that were
used to make them. So the first concrete
sample has 540 cubic meter of
cement, 0 cubic meter of blast furnace
slag, 0 cubic meter of fly ash, 162 cubic
meter of water, 2.5 cubic meter of superplasticizer,
1040 cubic meter of
coarse aggregate, and 676 cubic meter of
fine aggregate. Such a concrete mix which
is 28 days old has a compressive
strength of 79.99 MPa. The data is in a pandas
dataframe and named concrete_data. So
let's say we would like to use the Keras
library to quickly build
a deep neural network to model this
dataset, and so we can automatically
determine the compressive strength of a
given concrete sample based on its
ingredients. So let's say that the deep
neural network that we would like to
create takes all the eight features
as input, feeds them into a hidden layer
of five nodes, which is connected to
another hidden layer of five nodes, which
is then connected to the output layer
with one node that is supposed to output
the compressive strength of a given
concrete sample. Note that usually you
would go with a much larger number of
neurons in each hidden layer like 50 or
even 100, but we're just using a small
network for simplicity. Notice how all
the nodes in one layer are connected to
all the other nodes in the next layer.
Such a network is called a dense network.
Before we begin using the Keras library,
let's prepare our data and have it in
the right format. The only thing we would
need to do is to split the dataframe
into two dataframes, one that has the
predictors columns and another one that
has the target column. We will also name
them predictors and target. Now prepare
to see the magic of Keras and how
building such a network and training it
and using it to predict new samples can
be achieved with only few lines of code.
The first thing you will need to do is
import Keras and the Sequential model
from "keras.models".  Because our
network consists of a linear stack of
layers, then the Sequential model is what
you would want to use. This is the case
most of the time unless you are building
something out of the ordinary. There are
two models in the Keras library. One of
them is the Sequential model and the
other one is the model class used with
the functional API. So to create your
model, you simply call the Sequential
constructor. Now building your layers is
pretty straightforward as well.
For that, we would need to import the "Dense"
type of layers from "keras.layers".
Then we use the add method to add each
dense layer. We specify the number of
neurons in each layer and the activation
function that we want to use.
As per our discussion in the video on activation
functions, ReLU is one of the
recommended activation functions for
hidden layers, so we will use that. And
for the first hidden layer we need to
pass in the "input_shape" parameter, which
is the number of columns or predictors
in our dataset.
Then we repeat the same thing for the other hidden layer,
of course without the input_shape parameter,
and we create our output layer with one
node. Now for training, we need to define
an optimizer and the error metric. In the
previous module, we used gradient descent
as our minimization or optimization
algorithm, and the mean squared error as
our loss measure between the predicted
value and the ground truth. So we will
stick with that and use the mean squared
error as our loss measure. As for the
minimization algorithm, there are actually
other more efficient algorithms than the
gradient descent for deep learning
applications. One of them is "adam". One of
the main advantages of the "adam"
optimizer is that you don't need to
specify the learning rate that we saw in
the gradient descent video. So this saves
us the task of optimizing the learning
rate for our model. Then we use the fit
method to train our model. Once training
is complete, we can start making
predictions using the predict method.
Below the video, you will find a document
with links to different sections in the
Keras library that you can refer to to
learn more about optimizers, models, and
other methods that you can use in the
Keras library. But this code snippet
here is typically all you need to know
to build a regression model in Keras. In
the next video, we will learn how to
build a classification model using the
Keras library.