Congratulations on completing this
course! Let's quickly recap what we
covered in this course. In module 1, we
went over a number of exciting and
motivating applications of deep learning.
We also briefly covered neurons and
neural networks in the brain to
appreciate how they inspire artificial
neural networks, and then we learned how
neural networks make predictions through
the forward propagation process. In
module 2, we learned how an artificial
neural network learns through gradient
descent and backpropagation. We also
learned about the vanishing gradient
problem, and which activation functions
are best to overcome this problem. In
module 3, we learnt about the Keras
library and how to use it to build
models for regression and classification
problems. In module 4, we learned about
supervised and unsupervised deep neural
networks, and we used the Keras library
to build a convolutional neural network.
Finally, I really
enjoyed putting this course together, and
so I really hope that you enjoyed it and
learned a lot from it.
It was difficult for me at some point,
because I had to leave out a lot of
details in order to keep it simple. The
point of this course was not to teach you
everything but to teach you enough to be
ready for more advanced courses on
deep learning, and to even start
learning independently if you wish. And I
think that you are there now. Thank you
for taking this course and I wish you
the best of luck!