Before we can start learning about how
neural networks learn and optimize their
weights and biases, let's learn about
gradient descent. If you already know it,
please bear with me, as I want to make
sure that everyone who's taking this
course is on the same page. Let's say
that we have some data, and here's a
scatter plot of the data. For simplicity,
I have generated data where z is twice x.
And say we want to find the value of w
that would generate a line that best
fits this data. To do that, we define a
cost or a loss function.
One common cost or loss function is the
one shown here as J, where we take the
difference between the z values and the
product of w and x's. We square that and
we sum the squared difference across all
values of z and x. The best value of w
would then be the value that results in
the minimum value of this cost or loss
function. Let's take a look at how this
cost function looks like.
What makes this loss or cost function
attractive is that it is a parabola, and
has one global minimum or one unique
solution. For the given data, the value of
w that makes this cost function minimum,
is w equals 2, meaning z equals 2x, which
would result in a line that fits the
points perfectly. This is a very
simplified example as in real world datasets,
the target variable z would be
dependent on more than one variable and
we can't just simply plot the cost
function and visually determine the best
value of the weights. So how do we
determine the best value of w. The best
value of w, or w's in case you have many
weights to optimize, is determined through
an algorithm called gradient descent.
Gradient descent is an iterative
optimization algorithm for finding the
minimum of a function. To find the
minimum of a function using gradient
descent, one takes steps proportional to
the negative of the gradient of the
function at the current point.
What does that mean? We start at a random
initial value of w. Let's call it  w0,
and say it's equal to 0.2, and
we start taking steps towards the green
dot which is w = 2. To determine
in which direction to move, we compute
the gradient of the loss function at the
current value of w, which is 0.2.
The gradient is given by the slope
of the tangent at w = 0.2,
and then the magnitude of the step
is controlled by a parameter called the
learning rate. The larger the learning
rate, the bigger the step we take, and the
smaller the learning rate, the smaller
the step we take. Then we take the step
and we move to w1. w1 is essentially
computed as w0 minus the learning rate
times the gradient at w0. This
represents the first iteration of the
algorithm. At w1, we repeat the same
process of computing the gradient at w1
and using the same learning rate to
control the magnitude of the step
towards the minimum. We keep repeating
this step again and again until we hit
the minimum or a value of the cost
function that is very close to the
minimum, within a very small predefined
threshold. Now when choosing the learning
rate, we have to be very careful as a
large learning rate can lead to big
steps and eventually missing the minimum.
On the other hand, a small learning rate
can result in very small steps and
therefore causing the algorithm to take
a long time to find the minimum point.
Now let's see how each iteration with a
learning rate of 0.4 affects the way the
resulting line fits the data on the left.
We initialize w to 0, which means z
equals 0.
It is a horizontal line and therefore the
cost is high and the line as you can
see is a bad fit. After the 1st
iteration, w moves closer to 2 and
because the slope is very steep at w=0,
the new value of w results in a
big drop in the loss function.
The resulting line fits better than the
initial one but there is still room for
improvement. After the 2nd iteration, w
continues moving toward w = 2.
Because the slope is not as steep as
before, the step is not as big but the
cost function still drops in value and
the resulting line is moving closer to
the ideal best fit line. The same
observation is noted with the 3rd
iteration, and the 4th iteration. After
4 iterations, you can see how we are
almost there at w = 2, and the
resulting line almost fits the
scatterplot perfectly. With each
iteration, the weight is updated in a way
that's proportional to the negative of
the gradient of the function at the
current point. Therefore, if you
initialize the weight to a value that is to
the right of the minimum, then the
positive gradient will result in w
moving to the left towards the minimum.
Now that we understand how to optimize a
parameter that a function depends on,
we are now ready to start learning about
backpropagation and how neural networks
learn and optimize their weights and
biases.