In the previous videos, when discussing
how neural networks make predictions
using forward propagation, we assumed
that the network had optimized weights
and biases. But how do neural networks
train and optimize their weights and
biases for a given problem and data set?
Training is done in a supervised
learning setting, where each data point
has a corresponding label or ground
truth. And training is needed when the
predicted value by the neural network
obviously does not match the ground
truth for a given input. The training
process starts by calculating the error
E between the predicted values and the
ground truth labels. This error now
represents the cost or the loss function
that we discussed in the gradient
descent video. Therefore, the next step
would be to propagate this error back
into the network and use it to perform
gradient descent on the different
weights and biases in the network, to
optimize them using the same equations
that we saw in the gradient descent
video. So for our simple network with
only two neurons and that takes one
input, we calculate the squared error
between the ground truth T and the
predicted value a2. This represents our
cost or loss function. Of course normally
you don't train your network using one
data point but thousands and thousands
of data points. Therefore, the error is
computed as the mean squared error
calculated as follows. Then, we use the error
to update w2, b2,  w1, and b1 by
propagating the error back into the network.
For updating w2, we know from our
gradient descent video that we need to
use this equation to do that, but since
the error is not explicitly a function
of w2, then we will need to use the chain
rule to establish the derivative of the
error with respect to w2. So we know that
E is a function of
a2, and we know that a2 is a function
of z2, and z2 is a function of w2.
Therefore, we can take the derivative of
E with respect to a2, and take the
derivative of a2 with respect to z2,
and take the derivative of z2 with
respect to w2. Then the derivative of
the error with respect to w2 would be
simply the product of these individual
derivatives, like so. The derivative of E
with respect to a2 is -(T - a2)
and the derivative of a2 with respect
to z2 is a2(1- a2) and the
derivative of z2 with respect to w2 is
just the input a1. Therefore, w2 is
updated as per the following equation.
I'm assuming that you a're familiar with
differentiation, so I am going to skip
showing you how to find the derivatives,
but below the video you will find a
document that I prepared showing you in
details how to find each of the
derivatives shown here. Updating b2 is
exactly the same. The only difference is
the derivative of z2 with respect to b2
is 1 and not the input a1. Similarly,
we use this expression to update w1, but
the error is not explicitly related to w1.
So we again use the chain rule to
establish the derivative of the error
with respect to w1. We know that E is a
function of a2, and we know that a2 is
a function of z2 and z2 is a function
of a1, and a1 is a function of z1, and
z1 is a function of w1. Therefore, we
can take the derivative of E with
respect to a2, and take the derivative
of a2 with respect to z2, and take the
derivative of z2 with respect to a1,
and take the derivative of a1 with
respect to z1, and then finally take the
derivative of z1 with respect to w1.
Then the derivative
of the error with respect to w1 would
simply be the product of these
individual derivatives, like so. The
derivative of E with respect to a2 is
-(T - a2). The derivative of a2
with respect to z2 is a2(1 - a2),
and the derivative of z2 with
respect to a1 is w2, and the derivative
of a1 with respect to z1 is a1(1 - a1),
and the derivative of z1
with respect to w1 is the input x1.
Therefore, w1 is updated as per the
following equation. Using the same
approach we figure out the expression to
update b1. Now let's apply back
propagation to our example from the
forward propagation video. Recall that we
have a network of two neurons, with the
initial values of the weights and the
biases as shown. We apply forward
propagation and we calculate the value
of z1, which we found to be 0.415,
and the value of a1,
which we found to be 0.6023,
the value of z2 which we
found to be 0.9210, and
the value of a2 which we found to
be 0.7153. This
is the predicted value by the network
for an input of 0.1. Now let's
assume that the ground truth is 0.25.
We first compute the error between the
ground truth and the predicted value.
Next, we will start updating the weights
and biases for either a predefined
number of iterations or epochs, like
1,000 for example, or until the error is
within a predefined threshold of 0.001
for example. Using a learning rate of
0.4, let's see how the
weights and the biases change after the
first iteration. We already know the
expression to update w2, so we simply
plug in the
values of T, a2, and a1 to calculate the
gradient. The gradient of the error with
respect to w2 is 0.05706, and
therefore, w2 gets updated to 0.427
We repeat the same thing for b2. We plug
in the values of T and a 2 to calculate
the gradient. The gradient of the error
with respect to b2 is 0.0948, and
therefore, b2 gets updated to 0.612.
Similarly, for w1, we plug in the values
of T, a2, and w2, a1, and x1 to
calculate the gradient. The gradient of
the error with respect to w1 is 0.001021,
and therefore, w1 gets updated to
0.1496. As for b1, the gradient of the
error with respect to b1 is 0.01021,
and therefore b1 gets updated to 0.3959.
This completes the first iteration or
epoch of the training process. With the
updated weights and biases, we do another
round of forward propagation calculate
the predicted value and compare it to
the ground truth. Calculate the error and
do another round of backpropagation
Therefore, to summarize the training
algorithm: first, we initialize the
weights and biases to random values. Then,
we iteratively repeat the following
steps: 1. Calculate the network
output using forward propagation.
2. Calculate the error between the
ground truth and the estimated or
predicted output of the network.
3. Update the weights and the biases
through backpropagation. Repeat the
above three steps
until the number of iterations or epochs
is reached or the error between the
ground truth and the predicted output is
below a predefined threshold. In the next
video, we will continue our discussion of
the backpropagation algorithm and point
out a serious shortcoming of the sigmoid
function when used as the activation
function in the hidden layers of deep
networks.