In this video, we will discuss a problem
with the sigmoid activation function
that prevented neural networks from
booming sooner. This problem is the
vanishing gradient problem. Recall from
the previous video, with a very simple
network of two neurons only, the
derivatives of the error with respect to
the weights were as follows. See how
small the gradients are, but more
importantly, how small the gradient of
the error with respect to w1. Well it
turns out that because we are using the
sigmoid function as the activation
function, then all the intermediate
values in the network are between 0 and 1.
So when we do backpropagation, we keep
multiplying factors that are less than 1
by each other, and so their gradients
tend to get smaller and smaller as we
keep on moving backward in the network.
This means that the neurons in the
earlier layers learn very slowly as
compared to the neurons in the later
layers in the network. The earlier layers
in the network are the slowest to train.
The result is a training process that
takes too long and a prediction
accuracy that is compromised. Accordingly,
this is the reason why we do not use the
sigmoid function or similar functions as
activation functions, since they are
prone to the vanishing gradient problem.
Therefore, in the next video we will
learn about other activation functions
that became so popular and are now the
activation functions that get used
almost all the time in the hidden layers,
since they help in overcoming the
vanishing gradient problem.