As we discussed earlier, activation
functions play a major role in the
learning process of a neural network. So
far, we have used only the sigmoid
function as the activation function in
our networks, but we saw how the sigmoid
function has its shortcomings since it
can lead to the vanishing gradient
problem for the earlier layers. In this
video, we will discuss other activation
functions; ones that are more efficient
to use and are more applicable to deep
learning applications. There are seven
types of activation functions that you
can use when building a neural network.
There is the binary step function, the
linear or identity function, there is our
old friend the sigmoid or logistic
function, there is the hyperbolic tangent,
or tanh, function, the rectified linear
unit (ReLU) function, the leaky ReLU
function, and the softmax function. In
this video, we will discuss the popular
ones, which are the sigmoid, the
hyperbolic tangent, ReLU, and the softmax
functions. This is the sigmoid function.
At z = 0, a is equal to 0.5 and when z
is a very large positive number, a is
close to 1, and when z is a very large
negative number, a is close to zero.
Sigmoid functions used to be widely used
as activation functions in the hidden
layers of a neural network. However, as
you can see, the function is pretty flat
beyond the +3 and  -3
region. This means that once the function
falls in that region, the gradients
become very small. This results in the
vanishing gradient problem that we
discussed, and as the gradients approach
0, the network doesn't really learn.
Another problem with the sigmoid
function is that the values only range
from 0 to 1. This means that the sigmoid
function is not symmetric around the
origin.
The values received are all positive.
Well, not all the times would we desire
that values going to the next neuron be
all of the same sign. This can be
addressed by scaling the sigmoid
function, and this brings us to the next
activation function: the hyperbolic
tangent function. This is the hyperbolic
tangent, or tanh, function. It is very
similar to the sigmoid function. It is
actually just a scaled version of the
sigmoid function, but unlike the sigmoid
function, it's symmetric over the origin.
It ranges from  -1 to +1.
However, although it overcomes the lack
of symmetry of the sigmoid function, it
also leads to the vanishing gradient
problem in very deep neural networks. The
rectified linear unit, or ReLU, function
is the most widely used activation
function when designing networks today.
In addition to it being nonlinear, the
main advantage of using the ReLU,
function over the other activation
functions is that it does not activate
all the neurons at the same time.
According to the plot here, if the input
is negative it will be converted to 0,
and the neuron does not get activated.
This means that at a time, only a few
neurons are activated, making the network
sparse and very efficient. Also, the ReLU
function was one of the main
advancements in the field of deep
learning that led to overcoming the
vanishing gradient problem. One last
activation function that we will discuss
here is the softmax function. The softmax
function is also a type of a sigmoid
function, but it is handy when we are
trying to handle classification problems.
The softmax function is ideally used in
the output layer of the classifier where
we are actually trying to get the
probabilities to define the class of
each input. So, if a network with 3
neurons in the output layer outputs [1.6, 0.55, 0.98]
then with a softmax activation
function, the outputs get converted to
[0.51, 0.18, 0.31]. This way, it is
easier for us to classify a given data
point and determine to which category it
belongs. In conclusion, the sigmoid and
the tanh functions are avoided in many
applications nowadays since they can
lead to the vanishing gradient problem.
The ReLU function is the function
that's widely used nowadays, and it's
important to note that it is only used in
the hidden layers. Finally, when building
a model, you can begin with using the
ReLU function and then you can switch to
other activation functions if the
ReLU function does not yield a good
performance. And this concludes this
video on activation functions. I'll see
you in the next video.